A Guide to the Paul F. Cranefield papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA156
Rockefeller Archive Center
Paul F. Cranefield papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1952-1988, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Cranefield, Paul F. (Paul Frederic)
Ackerknecht, Erwin Heinz
FA156
0.44 Cubic Feet 1 box.
1 box.
Biographical/Historical note
Paul F. Cranefield (1925-2003) was a physician and professor at the Rockefeller University since 1966. His laboratory focused on studies of the causes of cardiac arrhythmia. Dr. Cranefield was the editor of the RU-based Journal of General Physiology and has published articles in the histories of biophysics, psychoanalysis, and mental retardation.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 C850
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access note
Limited access. Donor's permission to Ackerknecht correspondence is required until 1 January 2020. Consult archivist for assistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Material received 1985 April 19.
Medical education; Physics; Biology -- Research; Biophysics; Medical sciences; Medical research; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Cranefield, Paul F. (Paul Frederic); Ackerknecht, Erwin Heinz
- Erwin H. Ackerknecht Correspondence, 1952-1988, undated; 1; 0.4 Cubic Feet
  Biographical/Historical note
  Erwin H. Ackerknecht (1906-1988) was a professor of the history of medicine. He was director of the Institute of the History of Medicine at the University of Zurich from 1957 until his retirement in 1971. Dr. Ackerknecht supervised 155 dissertations primarily in the history of medicine, about 140 of which were at Zurich. Prior to his position in Zurich, German-born Ackerknecht was the first professor of the history of medicine at the University of Wisconsin at Madison (1947-1957).
  In his youth, Ackerknecht was involved in radical left-wing politics in Germany. There, he became associated with Leon Trotsky. In early 1933, Ackerknecht went underground and later fled Nazi Germany to France. By 1938, Ackerknecht had philosophically broken with the radical left and became a staunch centrist democrat.
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists primarily of correspondence by E.H. Ackerknecht to P.F. Cranefield. Also includes obituary material on Ackerknecht.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Donor permission required until 1 January 2020.
  - 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1955-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - undated, fragments (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Erwin H. Ackerknecht obituary, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)